<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Corona charitatis, = The crovvne of charitie a sermon preacht in Mercers Chappell, May 10. 1625. at the solemne funerals of his euer-renowmed friend, of precious memory, the mirroir of charitie, Mr. Richard Fishburne, merchant, and now consecrated as an anniuersary to his fame; by Nat: Shute, rector of the parish of Saint Mildred in the Poultry, London.</title>
            <author>Shute, Nathaniel, d. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852497</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852497</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17822</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12160)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17822)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1291:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Corona charitatis, = The crovvne of charitie a sermon preacht in Mercers Chappell, May 10. 1625. at the solemne funerals of his euer-renowmed friend, of precious memory, the mirroir of charitie, Mr. Richard Fishburne, merchant, and now consecrated as an anniuersary to his fame; by Nat: Shute, rector of the parish of Saint Mildred in the Poultry, London.</title>
                  <author>Shute, Nathaniel, d. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby for Samuel Man, dwelling at the Swanne in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fishburne, Richard, d. 1625.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17822:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Corona Charitatis,</hi> THE CROWNE OF CHARITIE: A Sermon Preacht in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers Chappell, <hi>May</hi> 10. 1625. at <hi>the ſolemne Funerals of his euer-renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> Friend, of precious memory, the <hi>Mirroir of</hi> Charitie, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. RICHARD FISHBVRNE, <hi>Merchant, And now</hi> conſecrated as an <hi>Anniuerſary to his</hi> FAME;</p>
            <p>By NAT: SHVTE, Rector of the Pariſh of Saint Mildred <hi>in the Poultry,</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>NVM. 23.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let me dye the death of the righteous, and let my laſt end be like his.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Si non vacat omnes paginas Scripturarum euoluere, tene Charitatem, &amp; in ea inuenies omnem ſcientiam. </p>
               <bibl>B. <hi>AVG. de temp. Serm. 39.</hi>
               </bibl> 
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Libri aspecti non placent, ſed inſpecti, </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LIPSIVS Prolog. Politic.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by W. STANSBY for SAMVEL MAN, dwelling at the <hi>Swanne</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17822:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17822:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS MOST WORTHY AND MVCH honoured friend, Maſter IOHN BROWNE Merchant.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S you had a Partner-ſhip, in ſeruice, in eſtate, nay in the hearts each of other, with that euer-memorable Partner and brother of yours, Maſter <hi>Richard Fiſhburne,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in health, but most plainely in the time of his ſickneſſe, by your mutuall teares often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times interchangeably anſwering each other, ſo ſo giue mee leaue I pray you to make you Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſtill in this Worke, for I conſecrate this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:17822:3"/> booke to your liuing Perſon, and to his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Memorie. To caſt freſh flowres of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation vpon him that is gone, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, were but to moue you to a new regret, and ſorrow for him, nay it were to lend eyes to the Eagle. To tell you that which you knew better then my ſelfe. To write of you, not what you deſerue, but what I owe, I dare not, leſt the leaſt ſuſpition might take you, that I did not write but paint, nay, not paint but dawbe; For I ſo farre vnderſtand you, that you loue not the common varniſh of the world, and that you turne in the faireſt part of your abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from the ordinarie view; wherein I must needes ſay, you much honour your ſelfe, and ſhew your ſelfe a true Diamond, which Artists beſt diſcerne, by ſhining in the darke, it being as great wiſedome in our ſufficiencie not to know our ſelues, as it is in our wants to know our ſelues.<note place="margin">Sicut liuoris nota eſt ſilere quod nouera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ita crimen eſt non enarrare quod ſenſeram Fulgent Car. Mytholog. l. 2.</note> Onely herein your modeſtie diſaccomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates your friends, while it will not admit, no not a deſerued thankfulneſſe. And I my ſelfe while I feare by writing what I might to flatter you, am forced by not writing, in a manner to be vnthankfull. Yet I conſider againe, that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="tcp:17822:3"/> is but a weake reflexion of a ſtronger affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and no true friend when hee writes moſt, yet hath that gift to write as fully as hee loues: therefore inſtead of my pen I encloſe my heart in this ſmall leafe, and preſent them both together for a token of my ſinceritie to you; and becauſe I may not bee ſo thankfull for that loue of yours which is paſt, my reſolution is with me to promiſe you my beſt ſeruice to come; An inſtance of which in ſhort (becauſe an Epiſtle as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. 45.</note> muſt not fill the Readers hand) is this little booke which I now dedicate to you, the firſt Commencement and beginning of my labours in this kind, and vndertaken not for the burniſhing of mine owne name (as mine owne conſcience dictates vnto mee) but for the lengthning of his memorie, who was your deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-accounted Partner, and my deepely-eſteemed friend. Accept it I beſeech you, for the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſake, it is of Charitie, a vertue, I know you loue with the very inſide of your heart, accept it for his ſake whoſe Character it is, with whom as you were Partner on earth, ſo I pray you may be Partner with him in heauen. Nay ſuch a claime your owne goodneſſe hath giuen
<pb facs="tcp:17822:4"/> mee in you, and ſuch ground haue I gotten of you by your fauours, that J dare intreat you to accept it for mine own ſake, as proceeding from that heart that hath no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of diſſimulation in it &amp; from him, who vowes himſelfe</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt obſeruant, and euer affectionate poore friend in life and death.</hi> Nat. Shute.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17822:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL THE Maſter, Wardens, Aſsiſtants and Commonaltie of the Myſterie of the MERCERS <hi>of the Citie of</hi> LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue not without faire cauſe inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed this Sermon vnto you. Firſt, It was preacht in that ſacred Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference and Aſſembly, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you were a principall part: Secondly, it was preacht
<pb facs="tcp:17822:5"/> vpon your owne ground, euen in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of your owne <hi>Bethell,</hi> your owne Chappell. Thirdly, it was preacht for one, who was, not long ſince a conſpicuous member of your Company, and one, who hath laid vp his greateſt truſt, for the decur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of many great workes of Charitie, in your faithfull hands. As it is then iuſtly conſecrated vnto you, ſo I deſire you to receiue it with the right hand, that it may paſſe vnder the Conuoy of your worthy names; This is the firſt time, that euer I ſet to Sea in this publike manner, that euer my Name came into the Printer's ſtockes.</p>
            <p>And though I haue not wanted that, which is now made the common bridge of Pretence vnder which moſt Bookes paſſe, I meane the Abetting of diuers friends to theſe Publications; nor yet I thank my God ſome ſmall thongs of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner abilities in my ſelfe, yet had it not bin, out of conſcience of my thankfulneſſe to my bleſſed friend of euer-deere memorie, rather to keepe vp his Remembrance, then to ſpread mine owne, I would ſtill haue
<pb facs="tcp:17822:5"/> kept mine owne priuate way, and neuer haue rode in the common duſt. But ſo ſweet was the thought of his tender affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction euer vnto mee, that I could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine reſt of my ſelfe by erecting him a monument onely in mine owne heart, but that I muſt preſent this walking monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him in paper to all the World, and firſt to you. Nay, ſooner had this ſmall Barke of mine floated abroad, but that the laſt yeere God troubled our wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and turned them into bloud. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, I hope it is not out of ſeaſon, for a man that cannot ſerue the Occaſion, and pay at day, to pay a due debt, when the Occaſion ſerues him: though I could not by reaſon of that ſtorme put out im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after his death: yet now it comes as an <hi>Anniuerſary,</hi> at the end of a yeere, to kindle his Memory once againe.</p>
            <p>Therefore I humbly craue, that you would bee pleaſed to lodge theſe poore labours in your good opinions, and the rather for his ſake, whoſe goodneſſe yet ſparkles in your eyes, and the Image of whoſe vertues is in this little Codicill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented
<pb facs="tcp:17822:6"/> to you. So ſhall you binde vp his Name in your owne names: And further beare a ſtrong obligation of Reſpect and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie ouer</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips moſt deuoted poore friend and Seruant, <hi>NAT. SHVTE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17822:6"/>
            <head>THE CROWNE OF CHARITIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>The Text NEHEM. 13.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Remember me, O my God, concerning this, and wipe not out my good deeds that I haue done for the houſe of my God, and for the offices thereof.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen firſt mine eye fell vpon this Text, no ſooner began I to ſee, then to wonder, much like a Goldſmith, who being to touch ſome old Coine, firſt wonders at the ſtampe, and then tries it; ſo was it with me; I being to take vp this ſheckell of the <hi>Sanctuary;</hi> to ſatisfie the preſent occaſion, I did long admire the confidence of the words; before I durſt once aduenture to touch the matter: But after ſecond thoughts, which like good Merchandize euer riſe better and better, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out the workes of this <hi>Princely</hi> ſpeaker, I ceaſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17822:7"/> to wonder at his wordes, and beganne to wonder at his workes; This <hi>Nehemiah</hi> the <hi>Authour</hi> of theſe wordes, was by birth a <hi>Iew,</hi> by preſent condition a <hi>Captiue,</hi> in a ſtrange ſoile; where yet hee grew high and flouriſht in the eſtimation of the <hi>King</hi> of thoſe <hi>Lands,</hi> and became his <hi>Cupbearer:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.11.</note> vpon which preferment, his purpoſe was not, as many men doe, to build his owne fortunes, and by regarding his owne skinne, to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the bodie of the Church and Common-wealth; But like an obedient <hi>Child</hi> to his owne Mother Country, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed all his thoughts how he might now refreſh and repaire decayed <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> To this purpoſe, hee firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints <hi>Heauen</hi> with his intention,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.5.</note> and prayes to <hi>God;</hi> Next hee ſpreads his requeſt humbly before the <hi>King:</hi> no ſtring left hee vntouched to fetch about this reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Hee</hi> vndertakes his iourney to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> viewes, no doubt, with a watery eye, and lookes through his teares vpon the miſerable breaches thereof,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.14.</note> and as <hi>hee found a place, where his beast vnder him could not paſſe;</hi> ſo hee might now well conceiue that hee himſelfe might finde ſuch a worke; as he could not eaſily paſſe. Men thought that to build <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was to make burnt ſtones whole againe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 4 2. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>Will they reuiue the ſtones out of the heapes of the rubbiſh which are burnt;</hi> yet <hi>Charitie</hi> thinks nothing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible: <hi>it belieues all things;</hi> hee teacheth his hand to worke, and begins it, yea not withſtanding the deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.1.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.6.12. <hi>Cic. pro Seſtio.</hi>
               </note> conſpiracies and calumniations of his enemie; nay, the hiring of the tongue of a falſe <hi>Prophet,</hi> to forbid men as it were from <hi>Heauen;</hi> he goes on <hi>acri animo,</hi> as the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators Phraſe is with a keene ſpirit to finiſh the worke; Euen with ſuch a tide and current of valour as that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.15.</note> nor his brethren, <hi>nor his ſeruants, nor the men of the guard put off there clothes ſaue only for waſhing,</hi> and that for two and fifty dayes together; I omit and flye ouer the publicke adminiſtration of his office, as he was <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17822:7"/> of the Land, his care for the <hi>Ministers</hi> and the ſeruice of <hi>God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull. de pallio. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> in all which reſpects I might crowne him with the ſpeech of the Father; he was <hi>Rex ſola gloria minor;</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi> inferiour to nothing, but to glory it ſelfe; No maruell therefore, if wee ſee ſuch a fiery ſtreame of confidence in his words, and ſo neere a line of familiaritie with <hi>God; Nulli ita Deo familiares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. Emiſlen homil. <hi>21.</hi> poſt Pentecoſt.</note> 
               <hi>ſicut bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Reges;</hi> None ſo familiar with <hi>God,</hi> as good <hi>Kings;</hi> The cleereſt bloud makes the beſt ſpirits, and a good life the greateſt confidence; The pureſt aire breeds the greateſt agility, and the pureſt life the faireſt hope, of which we haue here a full example; <hi>Remember me; O my God, concerning this, and wipe not out my good deeds, that I haue done for the houſe of my God, and for the offices thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text is a Prayer in which there bee two things;<note place="margin">Diuiſ.</note> the matter or the things deſired, <hi>Remember mee, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this, and wipe not out my good deeds that I haue done for the houſe of God and for the offices thereof,</hi> Secondly, the manner, familiarly in theſe tearmes, <hi>O my God,</hi> twiſe expreſſed: the matter of his requeſt for a reward, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in two ſorts, firſt, affirmatiuely, <hi>Remember me,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by way of negation, <hi>wipe not out my deeds;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe deeds; firſt, he mentions one in particular, namely, the prouiſion for the <hi>Leuits</hi> and <hi>Singers</hi> of the Temple; <hi>Remember me concerning this,</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.10:</note> hee mentions them indefinitely, <hi>Deeds</hi> in the plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; theſe <hi>deeds</hi> are deſcribed; firſt, by their adiunct: They are <hi>good deeds,</hi> Secondly, by their obiect, and that is double: firſt, <hi>For the houſe of my God,</hi> Secondly, <hi>for the offices thereof.</hi> Theſe bee the ſeuerall beames of this diuine light ſhining in this Text, Let vs now through <hi>God,</hi> looke vpon the firſt.</p>
            <p>God cannot properly be ſaid to remember,<note place="margin">Remember mee.</note> as man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers. There is a double memory in man, firſt, ſenſitiue, which is common with the beaſts, when the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17822:8"/> or ſpecies of any obiect, ſeene, heard, ſmelt, taſted or felt, (after the obiect is gone, and it ſelfe vaniſhed out of the fancy, is reduced againe into the phantaſie, either by the repreſentation of the ſame indiuiduall obiect, which was before or of ſome like vnto it; as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a beaſt, being well fed in an Inne, when hee comes to the ſame Inne againe, or one like it, he remembers it, and there turnes in. Secondly, there is an Intellectiue memory, when not only by a repreſentation of the ſame, or the like obiect, we reduce a thing into memory, but by diſcourſe, <hi>Ab hoc in hoc,</hi> as the Schooles ſay, from one thing to another, which the beaſts cannot doe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is called in the beaſts, memory, but in man, <hi>Reminiſcentia,</hi> that is, remembrance. Now neither of theſe memories are properly in <hi>God:</hi> Firſt, <hi>God</hi> hath no ſenſitiue memory, for hauing no ſenſible organs, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue any ſenſible repreſentations. Secondly, he hath no Intellectiue memory by intelligible repreſentations either created, or acquiſite, by which Angels and men vnderſtand, for he vnderſtands by no other meane, but by his owne eſſence.</p>
            <p>But he is ſaid to remember improperly, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to mans capacitie, when hee ſhewes mercy to his creature, either without promiſe, <hi>God remembred</hi> Noah <hi>and euery liuing thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105 8. <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7</note> or with promiſe, <hi>He hath remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred his couenant for euer, Tunc dicitur Deus meminiſſe quando facit; tunc obliuiſci, quando non facit; nam ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuio cadit in Deum, quia nullo modo mutatur: ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datio, quia non obliuiſcitur.</hi> God is then ſaid to remember, when he doth, and then to forget, when he doth not; for neither forgetfulneſſe is incident to God, becauſe hee is no wayes changed; neither yet remembrance, becauſe he doth not forget.</p>
            <p>So then, <hi>Nehemiahs, Remember me,</hi> is no more, then doe for me, O <hi>Lord,</hi> and let mee find a reward with thee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17822:8"/> through thy mercie, euen as I haue beene an Inſtrument of thy glory, and haue wrought for thee; from this expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhoot forth two concluſions, firſt, on <hi>Gods</hi> part in the word <hi>remember;</hi> to remember with <hi>God,</hi> is to doe; when <hi>God</hi> ſpeaks, he does, <hi>He ſpake and it was done,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.9. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.15.</note> when he heares, he grants, <hi>If we know that he heare vs, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we aske, we know, that wee haue the petitions, that wee deſired of him;</hi> when he knowes, he helps; <hi>Take no thought,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.31.32.</note> 
               <hi>ſaying what ſhall we eat, or what ſhall we drinke, for your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father knoweth; that yee haue need of all things:</hi> now what comfort could once draw neere vnto the ſoule of man, out of this that God knew our wants, if Gods knowledge were not a helpe withall? yea, when hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members, he doth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 1.72.</note> 
               <hi>To performe the mercy promiſed to our forefathers, &amp; to remember his holy couenant;</hi> Gods perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance and his remembrance goe together as the light and the Sunne; which notes the propenſion that is in God to mercy, to whom, in giuing helpe to man, it is enough to remember him; whoſe memory, and mercy are but as it were one act; and againe to vs it is an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; that our memories may guide our hands to mercy, and that we ſhould in a manner; as ſuddenly, relieue our brethrens wants, as we doe remember them; The ſecond <hi>Concluſion,</hi> Is, on <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> part, expreſſed in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle <hi>me;</hi> by which he deſires a reward from God for his good deeds. A requeſt, I confeſſe, full of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or liberty, wherein, as the word imports,<note place="margin">Remember mee. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Phauorin. v.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Budaeus v.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note> a man may ſay any thing to God, in a holy manner; yet for all this, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full enough.</p>
            <p>It is lawfull to thinke on a reward, yea to thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as a recompence. <hi>He had reſpect vnto the recompence of the reward.</hi> The word ſignifies to looke vp in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration curiouſly, which wee call in <hi>Latine Suſpicere.</hi> Secondly, It is not onely lawfull to thinke on it, but to ioy in it. <hi>Henceforth there is laid vp for mee a crowne of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17822:9"/> righteouſneſſe.</hi> Thirdly, It is lawfull to aske it, yea to aske it daily,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Thy Kingdome come,</hi> for whatſoeuer ſome braine-periſht Anabaptiſticall ſpirits think to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; the Lords prayer is to bee ſaid euery day, it is <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidiana oratio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Enchirid. c. <hi>71.</hi>
               </note> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine calls it,</hi> a daily prayer: thus <hi>Ezekiah</hi> when he ſtood in <hi>extrema tegula,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. epiſt. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Seneca's</hi> phraſe is, vpon the laſt tile, ready to leape downe into his graue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 38.3.</note> had his <hi>Remember mee, Remember now O Lord I beſeech thee how I haue walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and haue done that which is good in thy ſight,</hi> If any mans fancie worke him another way to thinke that <hi>Ezekiah</hi> deſired not a reward confidently, becauſe hee ſeemed by his teares to feare death; I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend this anſwer to him, hee wept not for feare of death abſolutely, but becauſe hee had no child to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in the throne of his Kingdome.<note place="margin">Hieron. in Eſ. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> For <hi>Manaſſes</hi> his ſonne, vpon whoſe ſhoulders the ſtaffe of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lay next; was borne out of the new leaſe of fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeeres; which God added euen three yeares after; not hauing climbed aboue the age of twelue yeares,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 21.1</note> 
               <hi>when he began to reigne; Ieremie</hi> had his <hi>Remember mee,</hi> and that with ſuch a pitch of confidence, that for my part, I thinke few or none dare pray his words after him <hi>O Lord thou knowest,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.15.18</note> 
               <hi>remember mee, know, that for thy ſake I haue ſuffered rebuke, wilt thou be altogether vnto me as a liar.</hi> If hee durſt thus far draw out his zeale, in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a temporall bleſſing, which is not to bee asked but as it were lamely, and with condition, what a riſe and aduantage will faith take for a ſpirituall reward? Shee will beg of God as freely, as euer <hi>Bathſhebah</hi> did of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>I deſire a petition of thee, I pray thee ſay mee not nay.</hi> Euen Chriſt himſelfe, as a man, deſired a reward of Glorie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.4 5.</note> 
               <hi>I haue glorified thee on the earth, and now, O Father, glorifie thou mee with thine owne ſelfe,</hi> whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample I haue reſerued like the beſt wine, to the laſt, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17822:9"/> no man, that hath his braines in his owne keeping, or hath his head about him, can now doubt that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to aske a reward with <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Prouided alwaies that in ſome meaſure or other hee bee a <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> that asks it, for this ſtrong meate is not for euery nouice, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can a ſmall ſtreame carrie ſo great a wheele; there are that dare not ſay, remember me <hi>for a Kingdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23.42.</note> but <hi>Remember mee when thou commeſt into thy Kingdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 9.49.</note> As amongſt <hi>Abimelechs</hi> ſouldiers, ſome cut downe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter branches, ſome leſſe, according to the proportion of their ſtrength, ſo among Chriſts ſouldiers, ſome car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a greater, ſome a leſſer confidence.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 27.44.</note> Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners ſome ſaued on boards, ſome on broken pieces of the Ship: ſo among Chriſtians, ſome arriue heauen, with one meaſure of truſt, ſome with another: All the members of the body, are knit vnto the head; but ſome nearer, ſome farther off; ſo in Chriſts body, all draw grace from him, yet in difference of grace, there is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of hope. Secondly, That the iuſt themſelues that haue this tranſcendent confidence, in asking a reward, doe not aſſume this out of arrogance of merit; for this ſtrong Harneſſe of merit, is onely fit for the Sonne of God; hee that ſaid here, <hi>Remember me,</hi> ſaid no more but <hi>Remember me,</hi> he ſaid not, reward me, according to my deſeruing; nay, after hee ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>Remember mee O my God, and ſpare mee according to the greatneſſe of thy mercy</hi> See how modeſtie and confidence at one time kiſſe each other. The Saints that are aſcended high in obedience, are like men gone vp high vpon a ladder; the higher they are gone vp, the faſter they hold; and they are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome paſſages of feare, to ſlip againe. Grace and merit fight like fire and water; the one puts out the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Tis a truth I confeſſe, beyond the line of all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; that, as the Rainebowe in the cloud, ſo peace in the conſcience, vpon a good ground is a faire ſigne of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17822:10"/> reconciliation; but yet withall, with <hi>Nehemiahs remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber mee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25.7</note> 
               <hi>Dauids</hi> remember me accords well; <hi>According to thy mercie remember thou mee for thy goodneſſe ſake O Lord.</hi> And thus much for the depth of <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in asking a reward;</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Wipe not out my deeds.</note>The ſecond terme which conueighs his requeſt for a reward, is in theſe words, and wipe not out <hi>my deeds;</hi> this being in a negatiue forme, as the other in an affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue: This word <hi>wipe not,</hi> hath a direct eye, or refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to that which the Sacred finger of the Scripture points at elſewhere, that a mans good deeds are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by God;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20.12</note> 
               <hi>The dead were iudged out of thoſe things which were written in the bookes according to their workes whether good or euill:</hi> Now there are three things of a good man written by God: firſt, his feare of God, <hi>A book of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance was written before him for them that feare the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16</note> Concerning whom, lend mee but your eyes a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſee what God ſaith in the next verſe, <hi>And they ſhall bee mine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith the Lord of Hosts, in that day when I make vp my Iewels,</hi> Theſe bee Gods prime ſeruants, his Iewels, the ſignets of his right hand, whom hee did not write in a booke, with the reſt of his Saints, but made a booke as it were, a part for them; and ſuch a booke, wherein they ſhould bee diligently remembred as the word imports. Secondly, hee writes our teares, <hi>Put thou my teares into thy bottle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sepher Siccaron.</note> 
               <hi>are they not in thy booke;</hi> God hath both a bottle and a booke for our teares; A bottle to put our teares themſelues in,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 56.8.</note> and a booke to write downe the Number, and the bitterneſſe of theſe teares. Thirdly, hee writes downe our good deeds, as in this place,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 70.</note> nay the word in the Greeke ſignifies as much as if they were not onely written but painted, yea, and that in oyle, for perpetuitie, O the infinite mercie of God, what tongue ſo rich, that is able to embelliſh it? Hee doth not onely write our names <hi>in the booke of life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20.</note> nay,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17822:10"/> write and engraue our remembrance <hi>in manibus ſuis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 49.16.</note> in the palmes of his hands, with great Characters, euen the nayles of his Croſſe, his bloud being his inke, his paper his owne fleſh, yea, <hi>our very members are written by him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.16.</note> but writes our workes and that ſo tenderly and fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 13.26.</note> that though our deſerts might ſway his hand to write bitter things againſt vs, yet he writes for vs.</p>
            <p>Mens Chronicles, the truer they are, the freer they are in taxing errors:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 21.17.</note> as an ingenuous Painter takes out the moles, as well as the fairer lineaments, <hi>The rest of the acts of</hi> Manaſſeh, <hi>and his ſinne that hee ſinned, are they not written in the Booke of the Chronicles of the Kings of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> but the vaines of Gods mercy are ſo large and full, that as he ſuffers his <hi>mercy to triumph ouer his iuſtice in rewarding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iac.</hi> 2.13.</note> ſo he ſuffers the ſame mercy to triumph ouer his truth in writing; and writes not our ſinnes, but only our good deeds; <hi>Gods</hi> Booke is not like a Merchants Booke of <hi>Creditor</hi> and <hi>Debitor,</hi> wherein a man writes, both, what is owing him and what hee owes himſelfe; for God in his mercy, wips out that wee owe him, and writes that only which he owes vs, by promiſe, much like the cloudes that receiue ill vapours from vs, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne them to vs againe in ſweet raines: that mans braine is yet darke, that doth not duly conſider this, for a great mercy; Againe, if God write vp our good deeds, this is as a full winde in our ſailes, to put vs on, euen to load Gods <hi>Chronicle</hi> with them; writing vpon our ſelues, by a reall profeſſion of his ſeruice, as <hi>Aaron</hi> did,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.36. <hi>Eſay</hi> 49.4.</note> 
               <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord.</hi> For, <hi>Surely our Iudgement is with the Lord, and our worke with our God:</hi> What mans heart ſo dry, that is not moued when he heares that <hi>our prayers and our almes goes vp for a memoriall before God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10.4.</note> not to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, as it were with one ſole act of his memory,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> but as the word carries it, to bee a ſtanding monument and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of vs for euer in his preſence: Shall our good
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17822:11"/> workes bee like <hi>Eſai's</hi> trees,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 10.19.</note> ſo few, <hi>that a child may write them,</hi> when we haue ſuch a God, for whom we worke, will not only thinke vpon our workes, but write them vp in ſuch royall paper as his owne Booke. Let no feare inuade vs, as if that paper could ſinke, and ſo wee ſhould loſe our workes, for if men loſe not ſmall deeds ſometime,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.18.</note> and <hi>Sauls</hi> teaching but of the vſe of a bow, deſerued a roome in a <hi>Chronicle;</hi> certainly better deeds ſhall neuer be blaſted, but <hi>God</hi> will write them and ſeale them vp for all eternitie. Secondly, as this word <hi>wipe not out</hi> implyes, that our good deeds are written by God, ſo againe it tels vs, that though they be written, yet they they may be wipt out againe, elſe had it beene in vaine for <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and a dead requeſt, to haue commended ſuch a petition to the eares of <hi>God,</hi> that his workes might not bee wiped out actually, had hee not firſt preſumed a poſſibility of wiping them out; For not to touch the skirts of the fierie hill, I meane the queſtion, of falling or not falling away from iuſtifying faith, or imputed righteouſneſſe; A man may fall away from ſome part of ſanctification, by a ſinne of prophaneneſſe, for he that ſo ſinnes, cannot be holy and vnholy in the ſame reſpect. As it is granted by all,<note place="margin">Enormibus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis pij reatum mortis incurru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Synod. Dordra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cena, c. <hi>5.</hi> artic. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that good men may fall into grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and ennormous ſinnes, ſo this inſtance following ſhewes that a contrarie act of prophaneneſſe muſt needs wipe out ſome part of ſanctification. <hi>Dauid</hi> chaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, falls into adultery, wee muſt needs ſay hee loſt that part of his holineſſe, except we ſay his adulterie was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which no man of the leaneſt vnderſtanding will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme.</p>
            <p>Now how farre, not one mortall ſinne, perchance originally proceeding from infirmitie, or precipitancie may quite eate out ſanctification, and ſo faith, as ſome ſay, (conſidering probably, that an habit of faith is not eaſily loſt, but may ſeeme to ſtand with ſome true acts
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17822:11"/> of inward Sanctification, ſome being loſt, as in another caſe, the foundation may ſtand, when the roofe or a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the houſe is falne) but many ſeuerall acts of foule and wilfull ſinning, without repentance,<note place="margin">Iude, verſe <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> not onely <hi>effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter.</hi> by acts directly contrary to the habit of faith, but <hi>demeritoriè,</hi> by acts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the habits of other vertues; when a man doth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſends away or caſts farre from him a good conſcience, as the word imports; how farre, I ſay, theſe ſinnes may make, or not make <hi>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fragium fidei,</hi> the ſhipwracke of faith,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>I will leane vpon the boſome of the Church, till it be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined;</hi> only I deſire leaue to adde my poore iudgement, which is, that if this queſtion and ſome others were not ſo rigidly ſtated, the diuiſion had not grown like <hi>Ahabs</hi> cloud from the bigneſſe of a mans hand to a ſtorme. But no more of this, becauſe my text is properly of wiping out deeds of ſanctification. Secondly, becauſe I can no more contract the whole diſcourſe of this argument within an houre, than all the beames of the <hi>Sunne</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a ring.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe in gathering herbes, I am loath to touch the wild Vine, or if I touch it,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4.39.</note> I will not gather my lap full, or if I gather it, I will not ſhread it into the pot of the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of the Prophets; I wiſh from the center of my heart, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> may not haue a wrinkle in her garment, not the leaſt contention; for, there is a feare beates vpon my heart; that when we haue ſtretched all the ſinewes we haue in theſe difficulties; we ſhall make but a <hi>Flemmiſh</hi> reckoning of them.<note place="margin">L. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Sozomen</hi> ſaith, that alwayes in the diſſention of the Church, the Common-wealth was alſo troubled; Therefore for my part, in my poore way, I ſhall bee readie to offer ſtill to <hi>Gods</hi> people the ſtaffe of bread, I meane the weightier things of the Law, and to keepe their braines from bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, with ſuch ſubtill lightning, as this is.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17822:12"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">My good deeds.</note>Now in this phraſe, <hi>wipe not out my good deeds,</hi> there doth further riſe vp before our conſideration what deeds theſe are;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.10.12.</note> Firſt, he ſpeakes of one in particular, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me concerning this,</hi> which was the ſuſtentation of the <hi>Leuits</hi> by the tithes of Corne, Wine, and Oyle, a worke of that grace and fauour with God, that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> dares begge a reward for it alone in particular.<note place="margin">Cum decimas dando &amp; terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na &amp; coeleſtia poſſis munera promereri quare per auaritiam duplici benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione te frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das? Aug. de temp. ſer. <hi>215.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me concerning this,</hi> Seeing by giuing of Tithes, thou maiſt obtaine both earthly and heauenly rewards, why doeſt thou by couetouſneſſe defraude thy ſelfe of a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bleſſing? ſaith Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> But becauſe this particular is drowned in the generall clauſe of his mercy, <hi>To the offices of the houſe of God.</hi> I only thus farre ſalute it, and next inuite you to his good workes in generall.</p>
            <p>And firſt I beſpeake your attention to the name of them;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>70.</hi> miſerationes meas. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgata miſericordias meas. Pagnin. pietates meas, Munſter. in loc.</note> The word in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſignifies as much as my mercies, and ſo doth the <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> render it, with others, becauſe he did it with a free heart, as <hi>Caietan</hi> ſaith, and not for humane fauour, but for Gods glory, as <hi>Lyra</hi> hath it; Euery mercie is a good worke, but euery good worke is not a worke of mercy. Two things make a good worke a worke of mercie: The firſt, is in <hi>ſubiecto,</hi> or him that worketh, when hee doth it freely without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of glorie or carnall profit to himſelfe, or others; and this is properly Grace.<note place="margin">Gratia.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeccond in the obiect, or the matter, vpon which we transfer our Charity, whether it be on men, or things belonging to God or men,<note place="margin">Miſericordia.</note> when they are in the iawes of Neceſſitie; and this is called Mercy. Both which condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were in <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> workes, for he did them freely <hi>ſine rimula Oſtentationis,</hi> without tha leaſt chinke of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation; and he did them mercifully, in caſe of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie; therefore his workes are not euery ſort of workes, but workes dyed in a deeper graine, they are mercies; but I cannot ſtand to view euery ſeuerall roome in my
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17822:12"/> Text: Time is my Maſter, I muſt ſubiect my ſelfe to him. And ſo I giue out from the name of theſe deeds, in the Originall, and come vpon the ſecond thing which is their Attribute, They are <hi>Good deeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The workes of good men are good indeed, firſt,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>5.22.</hi> Nihil à Deo non bonum quia di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinum, Tertull. de fuga in perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their efficient, <hi>God:</hi> who not only commands them, but produceth them: <hi>The fruit of the Spirit is Loue, Ioy, Peace;</hi> Now <hi>God,</hi> neither commands nor produceth any thing that is faulty. Nothing from <hi>God,</hi> but it is good, becauſe it is from <hi>God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Secondly, they are good in regard of the obiect and matter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iac.</hi> 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>Thou beleeuest that there is one God, thou doeſt well;</hi> Thirdly, in regard of the forme, whence they proceed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.18. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.27.</note> from a good heart purified by true faith, <hi>A good tree cannot bring forth euill fruit,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid of <hi>Ahimaaz; He is a good man and commeth with good tidings;</hi> ſo a good man hath good workes. Fourthly, in regard of the end; becauſe by them men intend Gods glory, their brethrens good,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22.</note> and their own ſaluation, <hi>If thine eye be ſingle, thy whole body ſhall be full of light;</hi> Euen as a good eye is the glory of the face, ſo a good intention is the glory of the action,<note place="margin">Ipſa iuſtitia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra vera eſt propter veri bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad quem refertur, Aug. de Ciu. Dei, l. <hi>19</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi> Bell. de iuſtific. l. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi> Stapl. de iuſtif. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; alii.</note> Our righteouſneſſe, ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is a true righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, becauſe of that end of true goodneſſe, to which it is referred.</p>
            <p>Our Aduerſaries then of the Chruch of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhew but the Canker in their mouthes and pens, to ſay and write, that wee hold good workes to bee ſinnes, nay, mortall ſinnes. For that we ſay may be put vp into theſe three concluſions. Firſt, that Good workes done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the conditions forenamed, are in the truth and ſubſtance of their nature, and of themſelues, good, yet by accident, they are, though not ſinnes, yet mingled with ſinne in that they paſſe through this channell of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, theſe graues of our concupiſcence, euen as water, of it ſelfe cleere, contracts corruption by running tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a foule pipe.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17822:13"/>
            <p>Secondly, They are truly good, but they are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, abſolutely, or meritoriouſly good, whereby a man may fulfill the law or deſerue heauen, as our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries would blazon it, for, for meritorious workes in the ſtiffe ſenſe of condignitie, it was neuer embraced of old,<note place="margin">Pueri. meritorij Cic. in Philip. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> nor yet can be, except it bee in one ſenſe, that wee call workes meritorious, as boyes or harlots are called meritorious, which deſerue rather ſhame or death, than a reward. Thirdly, yet doth not this accidentall min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling of our workes with ſinne, nor want of this abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perfection take away the kind or eſſence of our good workes. For the firſt: Though that Concupiſcence, which bliſters our good workes, bee by the law morall and in it owne nature, yet vnder Chriſt, a mortall ſinne (for Chriſt deſtroyed no part of the morall law, <hi>quoad obligationem obedientiae &amp; reatus,</hi> in regard of the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of obedience and guilt) yet <hi>quoad obligationem poenae</hi> in regard of the obligation of puniſhment; That which is mortall in it owne nature, is now not mortall, by effect through Chriſts death.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> 
               <hi>There is now no condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them who are in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>who walke not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit: And Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the Curſe of the law, being made a curſe for vs;</hi> a part of which curſe was,<note place="margin">Gal. <hi>3.10. D.</hi> Iohn White <hi>Way to the true Church.</hi> Digreſſ. <hi>37.</hi> Docet hoc tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm ad quam perfectionem contendendum ſit, ſed non obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat. Staplet. de Iuſtif. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Soto de iuſtit. l. <hi>2.</hi> q. <hi>5.</hi> a. <hi>4.</hi> co. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> that the law bound vs to beare the puniſhment of euery inconformitie to her, in thought word and deed; <hi>Curſed is euery one that continueth not in all things which are written in the booke of the law, to doe them;</hi> but now ſinnes of ignorance, infirmitie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſideration, are not through Gods mercie in Chriſt imputed to Gods children; and ſo doe not extinguiſh the workes of our true righteouſneſſe, neither <hi>make the workes looſe the name of good workes, nor put the doers into a ſtate of damnation,</hi> as a reuerend Diuine of late hath it. For though it is true that wee are bound ſtill to a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perfection of obedience, whatſoeuer our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17822:13"/> blab to the contrarie, who ſtill gather where it is not ſtrawne;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule, and withall thy mind,</hi> and that hee that is bound muſt needs incurre a guilt by breaking his bond, yet doth not that guilt in ſmaller things, now through the death of Chriſt and Gods mercie apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by faith, put him into a ſtate of damnation, becauſe one man at the ſelfeſame time cannot bee in a ſtate of ſaluation in regard of his faith and workes that pleaſe God, and in a ſtate of damnation, in regard of his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie imperfections; Water mingled with Wine doth not <hi>tollere ſubſtantiam vini,</hi> but <hi>diluere,</hi> doth not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſubſtance of wine, but weaken it; ſo our ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſinnes take not away the nature of good deeds, but doe weaken them, and make them leſſe perfect.<note place="margin">Malum per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens non deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it bonum per ſe.</note> Black ſprinkled vpon white doth not take away the whole co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of white but onely darkens it: ſo our good workes are not rooted vp by our infirmities, but onely defaced and obſcured. The law is like <hi>Sampſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 16, 20.</note> with his haire cut off, it goes out to ſhake it ſelfe as before, but it hath in this caſe no ſtrength to riſe againſt vs.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Gradus non mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat ſpeciem,</note> Neither doth the want of the degrees of abſolute perfection take away the kinde or ſubſtance of good workes, no more than the want of a finger the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a man; or the want of a fringe the ſubſtance of a garment. The imperfection of the worker is to bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſht from the ſubſtance of the worke. A man that is in cutting downe a tree, with an ill axe, cuts it downe in the end, though not ſo neatly; and a good man is ſtill deſtroying the body of ſinne by obedience, though it bee with ſome hacking and imperfection, but I will put out this lampe and conclude. Good workes are not ſinnes formally and properly taken, much leſſe mortall: but of themſelues and in their nature good; onely by accident mingled with euill, as appeares, euen by this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17822:14"/> one thing;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16.</note> that they pleaſe God; <hi>To doe good, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi> Now it is a thing againſt the graine, if not blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous, to ſay that a worke which is properly a ſinne, ſhould, though, by the indulgence of God, be pleaſing vnto God. But to turne mine hand from our aduerſaries to our ſelues, If our good deeds be good indeed, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but deepely cenſure them, that vnder pretence of aduancing faith, doe deuance good workes; and becauſe good workes are mingled with euill, therefore to make them cheape and contemne them, as if a man ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a beaten trauailer to ſeeke an vnknowne way, and to leaue the high way, becauſe there is a little duſt in it. What is this but to doe with Religion as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren did with him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 37.23.28.</note> ſtrip her of her parti-coloured coat, her robe of righteouſneſſe, and ſell her away to the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianites.</hi> Let vs baniſh this ſpirituall idleneſſe; Though wee receiue grace freely, and without labour at the firſt, yet wee cannot preſerue it without labour:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Concil. Nicaen. <hi>1.</hi> part. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi> A. Gell. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> ſay the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Fathers of the firſt <hi>Nicaene</hi> Councell. Thy labours proceeding from a ſincere faith and to a ſincere end, are not onely good in themſelues in the truth of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but notwithſtanding their ſmaller cracks and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, God will entertaine them as perfectly done; yea, crowne them in the end, euen as the <hi>Romans</hi> when they gaue the Obſidoniall Crowne to one that had deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered a Citie from the ſiege of the Enemie; made him a Crowne of that graſſe, and thoſe flowers, where the Citie was beſieged, ſo will God giue vs a reward of thoſe workes, which wee haue done well, for the glorie of his name, and the good of our brethren; Though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance our gold want ſome few graines.<note place="margin">Which I haue done for the houſe of God.</note> But all this while my Sunne hath ſhone through a cloud in generall, let vs now faſten our thoughts vpon the good deeds of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> in particular.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17822:14"/>
            <p>Theſe are of two ſorts, or haue a double obiect, Firſt, thoſe good deeds which he did <hi>for the houſe of God:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, thoſe which he did <hi>for the offices thereof.</hi> Firſt, <hi>for the houſe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Temple of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was called the houſe of God. Firſt, in a wider or larger ſenſe, <hi>ab efficiente,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as wee ſay, becauſe God commanded it to be built; <hi>Thy ſonne whom I will ſet vpon thy throne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>in thy roome, hee ſhall build an houſe vnto my Name.</hi> Secondly, more preſſely and in a cloſer ſenſe, in regard of the end, or vſe of this houſe; and that was double, Firſt, in reſpect of God, who dwelt in this houſe, and had poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it, that is, teſtified his preſence more cleerely there, then elſe-where, both in the <hi>Arke</hi> of the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and the Cloud; <hi>The Lord hath choſen Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8.6.11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.13.</note> 
               <hi>hee hath deſired it for his habitation.</hi> Secondly, in regard of his Seruice, Sacrifices, and Prayers, and other holy exerciſes being performed there by Gods people, therefore it was called the place: <hi>where his Name ſhould be,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8.29.</note> I might here bury a great part of my time, about the diſtinction and dignitie of the houſe of God aboue other places, not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated or made ouer, to Gods ſeruice; but I muſt draw in my ſailes. So I trauell on from the terme of the houſe of God, to place mine eyes vpon the liberalitie of <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> to this houſe.</p>
            <p>Vpon this houſe, beſides his flaming zeale in repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it, and the wall about it, he gaue with a full hand to the enriching of it <hi>a thouſand drammes of gold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7.70.</note> 
               <hi>fiftie Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. fiue hundred and thirtie Priests garments;</hi> a rich ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for euery able man to put vp vnto his conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it being a holy good worke, to doe good to Gods houſe: <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of our Fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 7 27.</note> 
               <hi>which hath put ſuch a thing, as this in the Kings heart, to beautifie the houſe of the Lord which is in Hieruſalem.</hi> They that built only the walls of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> yet are curiouſly regiſtred
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17822:15"/> in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> by the places which they repaired, by their names,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 3.5, 8, 9, 17 22, 32.</note> yea, by their conditions; for ſome were No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen, ſome Gouernours, ſome Leuits, ſome Prieſts, ſome Apothecaries, ſome Gold-ſmiths, ſome Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sulpit. Seuerus, hiſt. ſac. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Darius</hi> had three <hi>Hebrew</hi> young men, the Squires of his body, one among the reſt, by his wiſdome drew both the Kings affection and admiration vpon himſelfe; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon <hi>Darius</hi> bade him one day, Aske of him what hee would and he ſhould haue it, He anſwered, that he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nothing, but that <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> might bee rebuilt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Egnat. exempl. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Baron. ann. <hi>324.</hi> num. <hi>62.</hi> exactis Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſtri.</note>And Fame reports of <hi>Constantine,</hi> that in the erecting of a <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> he himſelfe carried out twelue baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets of earth vpon his owne ſhoulders, as appeareth by the foundation of the Church.</p>
            <p>What ſtrangers then are they to this <hi>Charitie of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi> who either demoliſh holy places, or through ſloth and couetouſneſſe ſuffer them to fall? Sure this is no <hi>Chriſtian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.1.</note> but a right heatheniſh tricke. <hi>O God, the Heathen are come into thine inheritance, thy holy Temple haue they defiled, they haue laid Hieruſalem on heapes,</hi> nay, the Heathen would neuer doe that to the Temples of the falſe <hi>Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leonte.</note> that wee <hi>Chriſtians</hi> doe to the houſes of the true God, for they hated and fled from all ſacrilegious perſons. Were the <hi>Church</hi> leprous, wee could doe no more, then plucke out the ſtones, as they did in the old Law;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 14.40.</note> in a Leprous houſe, nay, they would not, euen in ſuch a houſe plucke out all the ſtones, as they doe in Churches,<note place="margin">Conueniat me Ianus iratus qua velit fronte Tertull. Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. c. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> but only ſuch as were Leprous; Well let <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in his anger looke vpon me with either of his faces; (to borrow <hi>Tertullians</hi> words) yet I will euer proclaime, that, <hi>Next</hi> to the iniurie done againſt the temple of mans body, there can be no greater iniury then that which is done againſt the bodie of the Temple: And I wiſh that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17822:15"/> all ſacrilegious perſons, might feele the whip vpon their conſcience, which ſometime <hi>Celſus</hi> felt, who after the robbing of many Churches, hearing one day that place of <hi>Eſay</hi> read, <hi>Woe vnto them that ioyne houſe to houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. <hi>5.8.</hi> Gregor. Turon. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that lay field to field, till there be no place that they may be placed alone in the midſt of the earth;</hi> cried out immediately, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ae mihi &amp; filits meis,</hi> woe be to mee and my children.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Neither can they find in their hearts to bee on <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> ſide, who, in their hearts regard no Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor any publicke place conſigned to Gods ſeruice,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 14.23.</note> but build them as it were <hi>groues on euery high hill, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der euery greene tree;</hi> Or if they bee in the Temple, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themſelues there as reuerently, as in a Stable,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 7.25.</note> worſe than euer <hi>Hirams</hi> brazen Oxen; whoſe hinder parts were not to be ſeene in the Temple for modeſtie, but theſe mens Religion is rudeneſſe; as if Religion were beſt clad in a fooles coate;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Chryſ in. <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>14.</hi> hom. <hi>36.</hi> Exurge veritas &amp; quaſi de pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia crumpe, Ipſa Scripturas tuas interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, quas non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit conſuetudo. Tertull. deve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. virginibus cap. <hi>3.</hi> Pſal. <hi>102.14. And the offices thereof.</hi> Neh. <hi>7.1.</hi> &amp; <hi>13.10.</hi>
               </note> Iuſtly may wee complaine with Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> In the Primitiue Church houſes were Churches, but now Churches are as houſes, nay, worſe then houſes. But <hi>manum de tabula,</hi> I will put vp my penſill and conclude this point with that of <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Riſe vp O Truth, and breake from thy patience, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret thy ſelfe, thy Scriptures, which cuſtome knowes not; Neuer can that mans hand bee liberall to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that doth not firſt in his heart, <hi>fauour the duſt of the Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now as the faireſt houſe without a light, is worth little, nay hath no roome in our eſtimation, ſo the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Church without a Miniſter. Therefore <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was not onely liberall to beſprinkle <hi>the houſe of God,</hi> but <hi>the Offices thereof</hi> with his mercie: Hee appointed the Porters, the Singers, and the Leuites, yea a maintenance for them, without which the Prieſt-hood can no more ſtand then a plant without iuyce. And here wee haue found another freſh ſpring of his bountie: It is one of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17822:16"/> his good deeds, and our preſident, to let part of our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie fall vpon the Miniſters of God; were not this work a welcome and an acceptable worke to God, hee would neuer haue ſet ſo ſtrong a guard vpon the contrarie. <hi>Take heede to thy ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.41.</note> 
               <hi>that thou forſake not the Leuite, as long as thou liueſt vpon the earth.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Hee that receiues a Prophet in the name of a Prophet,</hi> that is, as the Father expounds it,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jſidor. Peluſ. l. <hi>4.</hi> ep. <hi>135 2.</hi> Chr. <hi>31.4.</hi>
               </note> not for indirect ends, but with a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked heart, looking to religion and goodneſſe <hi>ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a Prophets reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Hezekiah commanded to giue the portion of the Prieſts,</hi> the ſchedule or reaſon is annexed <hi>That they might be encouraged in the Law of the Lord.</hi> It is a laudable Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and ſuch as deſerues the ſiluer pen, to ſtill the cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bowels of the poore; yet if wee will lend credence to <hi>Aquinas;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quae ſunt ad finem, quanto ei propinquiora tanto meliora. Aqu. <hi>22.</hi> qu. <hi>81.</hi> a. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> That of thoſe workes which are ordained to one end as the glorie of God, thoſe are beſt which draw neereſt to the end, then muſt it needes follow, and weigh downe this conſequence, that the workes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Gods worſhip is maintained, becauſe they do more directly and immediately tend to Gods glorie, doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a larger table of commendation, then ordinarie charitie to the poore. They that annoint the skirts of Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons Garments, and they that annoint Aarons head, doe both repoſe their charitie in Gods hand; only thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it in Gods left hand, theſe in his right; pardon my zeale I pray you, if I ſeeme to ſcortch one ſide more then an other,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 17.8.</note> that Aarons rod may, if not flouriſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the reſt of the rods of Iſraell, yet flouriſh together with the reſt. I ſpeake not to take away the leaſt threed from the poore; but as it happens ſometime, that euen the faireſt coats of Armes may haue ſome barre or defect ſo may charitie to the poore (if it bee with a contempt of the maintenance of Gods ſeruice) looſe, if not the Principall, yet ſome part of the Intereſt of her commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17822:16"/> Neither doe I here ſerue our owne cauſe, to call vpon the maintenance of our perſons, without the ſeruice of God; but it is Gods cauſe that giues fire to this diſcourſe, For I could wiſh that the arke of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip might neuer ſhake, but God forbid that it ſhould bee ouerthrowne. In Gods cauſe, I dare throw a ſtone of reproofe againſt the face of ſuch as care not for the demoliſhing of Gods publick worſhip,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 17.10.</note> ſo euery <hi>Micah</hi> may haue a wandring <hi>Leuite</hi> in his owne houſe.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe it is, that they ſeeke out ſtaines in our coates, and in the publike Officers of the Church (as it is an eaſie thing to finde a ſpot in blacke) and being found, they waſh them ſo oft in Nitre and Fullers Sope, that in the end theſe garments are almoſt worne to rags. Well I ſay, <hi>If he that neglects to heare the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.7.</note> 
               <hi>muſt bee vnto vs as a Heathen man, or a Publican,</hi> hee that robs the Church is worſe then a Heathen or a Publican; to curtall the garments of the ſeruant of the moſt high God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues no better a reward;<note place="margin">Fulgos. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which <hi>Bambas</hi> the King of the <hi>Gothes</hi> gaue to <hi>Paulus Graecus</hi> the Church-robber to crowne him with a Crowne of Pitch. Let ſuch men conuent themſelues before their owne vnderſtanding; and they ſhall plainly ſee a direct tract of juſt feare in theſe ſacrilegious actions, namely, that he that alters Gods Decree concerning his ſeruice, many times rowles himſelfe into the ſame iudgement, which Hee incurred, that altered <hi>Cyrus</hi> his word, concerning his bountie to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> which was;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 6.11.</note> that a piece of timber out of his owne houſe ſhould bee his ruine. But now to ſeale vp this point. In <hi>Spaine</hi> of old,<note place="margin">Ammian. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. l. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> they that brought in the Euening Lights, cried <hi>Vincamus,</hi> Let vs Ouercome; as if the very light ſhould inflame them vnto Victory: ſo now haue we <hi>Nehemiah</hi> for a Light, I as your Seruant preſent this Light vnto you, and exhort you with all the bloud I haue <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incaemus,</hi> Let vs ouercome, Let vs ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17822:17"/> I ſay, our Hardneſſe with Liberalitie to Gods ſeruice, that <hi>God may remember vs concerning this, and neuer wipe out the good deedes wee haue done to the houſe of our God, and the offices thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus hauing lodged the colours and run out the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> Prayer, the manner of it, now attends your conſideration, wound vp in this familiar tearme, <hi>My God.</hi> But the houre is declined; and ſeeing I haue already compelled you a mile, I will not compell you twaine; And the rather not in this point, becauſe the matter of the Prayer, was the principall Land-marke or Beacon at which I aymed at this time, the manner, at leaſt wiſe, this manner of familiar Prayer, is no ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient into the eſſence of Prayer, but a degree of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Prayer. Therefore <hi>praeternauigabit oratio</hi> I will ſaile by it, and onely now retriue ſome few things ſpoken by way of concluſion, vnlade my ſhip perfectly, and put her vp into the creeke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Concluſ. Plin. l. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>Your eares haue receiued this day the ſteely confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> how like a true Eagle, he durſt looke vpon the <hi>Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> and aske a reward, I haue led you likewiſe to the golden anchor of his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>His good deeds:</hi> which with her two teeth, layeth faſt hold vpon his Charity <hi>to the houſe of God, and to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffices thereof.</hi> No ſweeter friend, no better compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then a good conſcience; nor no better deedes in the World to warme the conſcience with a comfortable hope, then theſe two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Micah</hi> the Idolater treaſured vp to himſelfe a ſweete content, by but an appearance of one of theſe actions; <hi>Now know I that the Lord will doe mee good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 17.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing I haue a Leuite to my Priest,</hi> what then remaynes, but that wee transforme our ſelues into this example? Let not our Aduerſaries grind the face of our Religion, to ſay Religion and Charitie were at one time thruſt out
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17822:17"/> of this Kingdome: Though wee haue ſent them their Religion, yet wee haue kept (and my hope yet liues) ſhall keepe their Charitie. For what is wealth, without the true vſe of it? no more then thoſe ornaments about the neckes of the <hi>Midianitiſh</hi> Camels;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 8.24.</note> the poore beaſts poſſeſſed them without vnderſtanding, and ſtrait-skind rich men poſſeſſe their wealth without true comfort. If there be any difference, here it is, that thoſe Iewels were bound to the Camels, but rich men more baſely are bound to their wealth. Againe, how quickly may death ſnatch vs away, as in a whirlewind, as hee ſnatcht away the rich man in a night, from his barne doores, who ſung a <hi>requiem</hi> to his owne ſoule, but neuer askt himſelfe, in what poſture other mens ſtates ſtood. Euen as a brooke, with a fall of raine waters, ſwels, and as if it were proud of his late increaſe, makes a noyſe, nay, runnes here and there,<note place="margin">Sicut torrens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis pluuialibus redundat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrepit, currit &amp; currendo decur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: ſic eſt omnis iste cur ſuo mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitatis, Aug. in Pſal. <hi>109.</hi>
               </note> to ſhew it ſelfe till by running it hath runne out all that euer it had: Euen ſo ſome rich men, vpon ſome fall of wealth begin to ſwell, as if they were little Seas; then make a noyſe of oſtentation, and becauſe they haue but one tongue of their owne, they get the Eccho of Flatterers; they ouer-flow the lower grounds, that is the poore, and ſpread their names in text Letters of bloud; in the end, after ſome ſhort noiſe, as the brooke leaues nothing, but mire; ſo leaue they nothing at their death to themſelues, but confuſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and men. And now to bury all the aſhes of this Sacrifice at the foot of the Altar, and to end my text, This is the common Sewer into which all humane vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie runnes: as <hi>Iulian</hi> ſaid when hee was taken in to bee <hi>Emperour</hi> with <hi>Constantius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nihilo ſe plus aſſecutam quam vt occupatior interiret Amm. Marcel. l. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> and ſome vnexpected miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe dropt vpon him. That he got nothing by his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement, but only to dye with more trouble; ſo this eſtate followes many times thoſe that haue eſtate, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Wealth abuſed yeelds no better crop then ſowre
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17822:18"/> weeds of diſcontent; to make a mans death bitter; Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the good mans death, is like Muſicke, though it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of Sharps, yet it ends in a Diapaſon, and with a ſweet cloſe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.32.</note> 
               <hi>The righteous hath hope in his death,</hi> Nay both in life and in death as the Prophet ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14, 2.</note> dareth to take words with him, and ſay, <hi>Remember mee, O my God, concerning this; and wipe not out my good deeds, which I haue done for the houſe of my God, and for the offices thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I fall downe from the Text to the occaſion.</p>
            <p>In all that whole row of ſolemnities, which men ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue on earth, there is none more powerfull to let down the heart of man, then the ſolemnitie of funeralls; our Churches mourne; our houſes mourne, wee our ſelues mourne, yea the very aire by a kind of repercuſſion of blackneſſe, ſeemes it ſelfe to be black; and mournes.</p>
            <p>The death of man in generall, is able to make our Sorrowes runne; what pittie is it that hee that euen now was Monarch of the aire; to breathe where hee liſted, ſhould by and by haue his lungs ſtopt with duſt, and bee lockt vp well-nigh for euer, in the breathleſſe earth? That he that had <hi>Gods candle ſhining vpon his head</hi> euen now,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 29.3.</note> ſhould preſently lay his head vpon the ſable pillow of the bed of darkneſſe? That hee that kept the beſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie with men,<note place="margin">Buxtorſ. Sina Iud. c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> ſhould by and by haue no other compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie but with wormes? If the Iewes in the feaſt of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation thinke the ſwealing of a candle ominous; what may wee thinke of the dying of a man? Certainly, if wee blow vp this powder into our heads, it will awake vs from our Lethargie; ſpecially ſuch, who take vp this conſideration withall, that the ſame death that ſlue their brother, may next tread vpon their heeles.</p>
            <p>But aboue all things my iudgement runnes this way, that the death of good men, ſhould make our vaines cold; when an ordinarie man breaks rank and dyes, there
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17822:18"/> falls a vapour, but when a good man dyes, there falls a Starre: when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhooke off <hi>Egypt,</hi> and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they robde the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> and when a good man ſhakes off the world he robs the world. Such was the death of this thrice-worthy and euer-renowmed <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Maſter Richard Fiſburne,</hi> whom death too ſoone for vs, though too late for himſelfe, hath with an <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> remoued into another world; So ſowre is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of it that my Prayers are riſing ſtill, that his death with other good men, may not be a lightning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a great thunder, and that the loſing of ſuch corner ſtones may not periſh the whole building. But before I ſpinne out the particulars of his vertues, I muſt firſt ſhape ſome Apologie, for my ſelfe and my dead friend of neuer-dying memory: On my part, ſome mens thoughts may bubble vp within them, and imagine that I ſpeake for my fee. Others out of a gloomy ſuſpition may conceiue, that there might ſome deſire ſtart from him, to haue his Sepulchre whited after his death; and this commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on painted vpon it, but I will put in myne anſwere. Firſt, for that imputation that may bee rolled vpon me; I doe profeſſe with an vntainted heart, that though I haue as good a cauſe, as a poore man can haue to dote vpon the remembrance of my friend, yet ſhall not any ſiniſter end, ſet my tongue on worke; further then the truth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands me.</p>
            <p>For him hauing now no relike of him, but only his <hi>Remembrance,</hi> (which is no more to a friend himſelf, then a ſhadow to the bodie) I will euer defend it, and keepe his name bright, from the ruſt of contradiction; yea, I ſhould ſlay mine owne conſcience, if I ſhould not wipe out the leaſt imputation that is caſt vpon him. Hee did diuers times, both in the beginning of his ſickneſſe and towards the end, grate vpon the abuſe of this cuſtome of ouer-ſpicing the dead in large commendation; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17822:19"/> me, yea, with ſome flaſhes of importunitie that I would performe this laſt office of Preaching for him, but ſpeake nothing of him; And indeed had it not beene, that by my ſilence I ſhould haue maymed the common expectation, his honour, and your example; I had turned theſe wordes into ſighes, and haue impoſed this dutie vpon mine eyes, and not vpon my tongue. But who can part with ſo good a man, ſo ſweet a friend, in ſo rude a manner, as to ſay nothing? If I muſt needes therefore erre one way (as in theſe occaſions commonly the wind ſtands in our faces, and our actions returne vpon vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine) I will rather be immodeſt in denying the modeſty of my friend, then vnthankfull in denying mine owne duty; And ſo I breake away from the Apologie to the matter.</p>
            <p>This brother of ours deceaſed, was by birth a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Towne of <hi>Huntington,</hi> cut out of no meane quarrie, borne of a good houſe, what the ſtrength of his education was, and how hee was tranſlated out of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, into Grace, ſhined cleerly in the vertues, lent him by God when more yeeres fell vpon him. Commonly the heate of good inſtitution which is put into a child yong, glowes in him little or much, while hee hath a day to runne through in this life; And as many times the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man, that hath the eye of experience, will giue a faire gheſſe of the whole day, by the morning: ſo many times to a man of a freſh ſight youth is an Optick-glaſſe to diſcouer afarre off, the ſequell of many yeeres; After that hee was well inlayed by his education, God hauing endowed him with excellent parts of Nature, hee was tranſplanted into the ſeruice of a Noble <hi>Counteſſe</hi> in this Kingdome, where (as the faireſt flowres haue often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the fainteſt ſmels) he did not long like the candied happineſſe of the Court. From thence therefore hee tooke his way into the Ciite, and became ſeruant to a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17822:19"/> Gentleman of full eſteeme and credit <hi>Sir Baptiſt Hickes, now Knight and Baronet,</hi> from whoſe owne mouth I heard it with what diligence and faithfulneſſe, euen for many yeeres together, hee diſindented and diſcharged himſelfe of that ſeruice.</p>
            <p>For his vnderſtanding, ſo much as might lye within the compaſſe of an ordinary braine:</p>
            <p>Fame it ſelfe could ſcarce lie of him; which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his he often watred with aſſiduous reading pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing in his ſickneſſe, the large comforts he had culled to himſelfe out of thoſe houres laid by for his priuate ſtudies. And this was aſcertain'd afterwards, by a Booke in <hi>folio,</hi> which bare the collections which he had fiſht out of diuers Bookes of <hi>Diuinitie, Historie,</hi> and the like.<note place="margin">Pet. Martyr. <hi>M.</hi> Perkins, &amp;c.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides by the voice of reaſon, it is commonly true, that hee that is prouident in his youth, is rich in his age; ſo he that is ſtudious of good things in his former yeeres, is all comfort in his death.</p>
            <p>Hee wsa an affable man, Hee that looked but vpon his face, might haue ſeene goodneſſe and courteſie looke out of his eyes. If a poore man, whoſe hopes perchance, lay a bleeding, had, had any requeſt to haue aduanced vnto him; he carried ſuch a dew in his lippes, and anſwers, that he would haue breathed, as it were another life in his face. His geſtures ſo without all ſpecks of offence, &amp; iniurie, as that he deſerued the name which <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third had for his modeſtie, to bee called <hi>Compoſitus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Volateran. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropolog. l. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> A man well compoſed, This was that which made him <hi>Lord</hi> of ſo many hearts. Scarce was there a man within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of our memory, that euer wonne himſelfe more loue in his health, more Prayers in his ſickneſſe, more lamentation after his death. Hee was a iuſt man in his words, yea, in his actions (for his actions did ſecond his words) He profeſſed vpon his laſt bed, euen on his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed where euery man ſpeakes, with an vnmasked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17822:20"/> that to his knowledge, he had not gotten any part of his goods iniuſtly. O bleſſed example! O rare preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent! In the large liſt of many Ages, but one man, euen <hi>Aristides,</hi> reacht the name of a Iuſt man; I could wiſh that the Embleme, which ſometimes <hi>Ferdinand Count Palatine of Rhine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iac. Typot. ſymb. Princ. tom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> made, might be ſet vpon our ſhop-wals, and Counting-houſes, which was, The Picture of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, taking her leaue of the World, and ſitting vpon a <hi>Dolphin,</hi> with a Ballance in her hand, and theſe three words written about her, <hi>Cognoſce, Elige, Matura,</hi> Know, Chooſe, Make haſte, Know that Iuſtice is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, Chooſe that which is iuſt, Make haſte, leſt by a momentany ſinne, thou bind thy ſelfe in euerlaſting pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. He was a religious man in priuate, His man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was, Before he would dip his hand in any publicke worldly action, his Prayers ſhould firſt lead him out of doores. For his vnderſtanding fauoured him ſo farre, as to know that it was Prayer, that like <hi>Rahabs</hi> Scarlet Threed in her window, gaue defence to our houſes, our perſons, and all.</p>
            <p>He was religious in publike, Hee was a frequent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent, attentiue, and impartiall Auditor of the Word. He was none of the <hi>Peripatetick</hi> Profeſſors, who haue a walking Religion, from one Church to another: and from their owne ordinary Paſtor to a worſe; much like the ſilly-hearted <hi>Doues,</hi> that for no reaſon leaue the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Doue-houſe, and build perchance in the next place they ſee, <hi>Barne</hi> or <hi>Steeple.</hi> O the ſtrangenes of theſe times! Religion, which was wont to haue but one face, is now a monſter; and hath many. Nay, there are ſome Miniſters, that haue ſo much ſtout bloud in their veines, that they ſtart not, to giue the people this ſowre milke, ſome indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, ſome directly, that this Sin to leaue their own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, is a part of <hi>Religion.</hi> Indirectly at mens tables, where euery Chaire is a Pulpit, they play vnder board and teach by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17822:20"/> it, by caſting a foame vpon their Brethrens names; and ſo draw all the water to their owne Mils. Nay directly, euen in the ſacred ground of Pulpits, ſome daſh through all manner of waters, and by briniſh declamations againſt others, wind all the beſt Threed vpon their owne Clues; Inſomuch that the Prophet's words whip our times,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.31.</note> as well as his owne, <hi>The Prophets propheſie falſely, and the Priests beare rule, by their meanes, and my people loue to haue it ſo, and what will yee doe in the end thereof?</hi> I ſweate not now, in hatred of any mans perſon; nor to beſmoake the weakeſt labours of any man, with the leaſt preiudice, ſpecially when they fall from a ſincere heart, But yet I hate Hypocriſie, as Hell it ſelfe; when a man for an ell of Lawne, more or leſſe, or a ſiluer Cup at a <hi>Christning,</hi> or hope of ſome Legacie at a mans death, ſhall vnwind his tongue, this way and that way, and euen rocke any cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, as we ſay, though of a baſtard, to fill his owne Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne with ſome water.</p>
            <p>Shall the Diſciples in a priuate houſe eate any tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall food ſet before them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.7.</note> and ſhall not the people in Gods Houſe eate the ſpirituall foode that is offered them?</p>
            <p>Shall euery man haue his owne ſet houſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 21.22.</note> to eate and drinke in, and ſhall Religion haue no certaine houſe to dwell in? I aske a man (if he haue the temple of his ſoule in his conſcience, not in his phantaſie) will hee ſay with a broad forehead that a Miniſter is bound to preach, and can hee ſay with narrow lips that the people are not bound to heare? Is it the ordinance of God, euen in the court of their owne iudgements, that a Miniſter ſhould preach, and doth not the ſame impregnable Ordinance lay hold on the people to yeeld their eares? Let them weaue this web a little cloſer; It is a booke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe in the Scripture, <hi>They that reſiſt the ordinance of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> receiue to themſelues damnation.</hi> Yea but they gruntle
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17822:21"/> and ſay they cannot edifie, and what then? <hi>Shall wee doe euill that good may come?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8.</note> Againe, to cut a little nearer the hoofe, it wants ſcarce a haires breadth of blaſphemie to ſay this, that they cannot edifie; For edification, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a worke of the ſpirit, is claſped to no certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or gifts; how powerfull ſoeuer in working vpon the affections; but to the Miniſterie in generall, The Goſpell in generall, in whatſoeuer Miniſter it is, it is the <hi>power of God to ſaluation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.</note> as the light in the Sunne is the ſame, in a cottage, as in a Palace. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Notwithſtanding euery way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>whether in pretence, or in truth, Chriſt is preached, I therein reioyce and will reioyce.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thou brayeſt yet, and ſayeſt, thou canſt not edifie, perchance the fault lyes in thine owne bones; either thou haſt not prepared thy ſelfe by prayer and repentance, or elſe thou art laden with a preiudice againſt the Preacher or elſe thou reſigneſt thyſelfe ouer to wandring thoughts and then no maruell, if hee that is ſtopt at the heart, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not breathe freely, and hee that hath an vnprepared, a preiudiciall, and an vnſtable ſoule, cannot edifie. Laſtly, though God hath opened the people a doore of libertie, to iudge of the doctrine of the Prophets, by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in things fundamentall and plaine, yet from what coaſt came their power or art to iudge of the gifts of the Prophets; whether by them they are able to edifie or no. Specially in one thing I am ſure, that their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment breakes not euen, who ſet a price on euery Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, not by his knowledge but by his zeale.</p>
            <p>If edification be no more then building, ſurely, hee that hath leaſt skill is the worſt builder, but I craue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, that I haue throwne away ſo much time to cut this weed ſo neere the ground. Let euery man looke to his owne hearth that the Sunne put not out his fire, nor his zeale his knowledge. To mee, it ſounds all one, for a man to leaue his Paſtour, and for a child to leaue his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17822:21"/> So to re-ſalute the occaſion againe, Hee was a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable man, charitable in his life time, while his health followed him, charitable when ſickneſſe arreſted him, charitable in priuate. He waſhed the feet of many poore and was ready as occaſions were put vp vnto him by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to reare vp all the children of Neceſſitie with his mercie; Nay he was not drie-handed to ſome Hoſpitals in priuate before his death, but bleſſed thoſe dead bones with his charitie, and obtained the name of a mercifull man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 22.28.</note> as the chiefe Captaine obtained his freedome with round ſummes of money? O beautifull charitie! The cloſeſt day the greateſt heate, and the water that runnes vnder the earth is euer the pureſt; ſecret charitie open vertue, <hi>Thy Father which ſeeth in ſecret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall reward thee openly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee was charitable in publicke, and that not in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls, but in ſheaues, I ſhall remonſtrate to you not a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble onely, but a field of mercy, not a paper, but a book of good workes; euen ſo large, that without the helpe of a Catalogue, my memorie would ſtagger in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſing of them. It is ordinarie, that no man almoſt doth all the good which another man remembers, but it is rare that a man ſhould not remember all the good which another man doth. I might here enterlace the Legacies of Nature, which hee powred into his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds laps;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth</hi> 3.15.</note> as ſometimes <hi>Boaz</hi> powred into <hi>Ruths</hi> vaile ſixe meaſures of corne: for, euen for this one principall beame of charitie, I may tranſlate that ſaying of the <hi>Canticles</hi> from thence, to this place; <hi>Wee haue a little ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and ſhee hath no breaſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.8, 9,</note> 
               <hi>what ſhall wee doe for our ſister in the day, when ſhee ſhall be ſpoken for? If ſhee bee a wall, we will build vpon her a Palace of ſiluer: and if ſhee be a doore, wee will encloſe her with boards of Cedar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing there is, the remembrance of which I cannot leaue hehind mee; and (to behead all vnneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17822:22"/> circumſtances) it was thus, A friend of his one day infuſed into him this particular, that in ſuch a place, there was a Gentlewoman attending vpon a Lady of good qualitie, who by meere chance hearing the name of <hi>Fiſhburne</hi> in diſcourſe at that time, preſently conceiued, that he was her kinſman, and with a winged deſire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly addreſſed her ſelfe to know the place where hee dwelt; and ſo for that time put vp her deſires againe. This Narration arriuing with Maſter <hi>Fiſhburne,</hi> he with a ſtrong gale of affection,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ne vogue de ſaueur. Prouerb Gallic.</note> beares now toward the place of this Gentlewomans abode; and there deſcrying this truth by liuely circumſtances, that ſhee was a ſtemme of the ſame tree of alliance with himſelfe; for that time moſt courteouſly entreated her, after, preſented her with no meane preſent, ſhortly gathered her home to his owne, and while breath was with him, nouriſht her with reſpect and bountie; and when hee was with the good <hi>Samaritane</hi> to leaue the Inne of this body, placed that care of her vpon his deare and worthy Partner, and Executor; and with a bleſſed hand caſt a thouſand pound vpon her. But I muſt ſup vp many things with a ſhort breath.</p>
            <p>I might here likewiſe diſh out his Legacies of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to his Maſter, and all his Maſters chiefe Allies, and to many other friends, and that not with a narrow hand, which very thing is not barren of his praiſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; For hee that is vnthankfull is not a Chriſtian, is not a man, no not ſo good as a beaſt; but a very dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, on which if you caſt neuer ſo ſweet odours, yet it will ſend you euill for good: I might here adde more links to this diſcourſe; and ſpeake of his Legacies of loue, which he deriued vpon his ſeruants; his memorie not ouer-leaping one that had beene with him, euen from ſeuen yeares before his death. Giuing to ſome tenne pounds, to ſome fiftie pounds, to ſome an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hundred
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17822:22"/> pounds, to ſome two hundred pounds apiece, a worke that hath the face of Charitie vpon it, as well as the other; But I muſt driue on a little faſter, to his weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier workes of mercie. To the Poore, and to the Church.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he laid his hands vpon the poore, and gaue,</p>
            <p>To the poore of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Hoſpitall a thouſand Markes.</p>
            <p>To the Hoſpitall of <hi>Bridewell,</hi> two hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>To Saint <hi>Bartholomewes</hi> Hoſpitall, a hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>To Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> his Hoſpitall, a hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> To the <hi>Mercers</hi> a thouſand pound for fiue young men of that Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, two hundred pounds apiece for fiue yeeres together <hi>gratis,</hi> &amp; ſo from one to another for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> To the Poore of Saint <hi>Bartholomewes</hi> where hee liued, fiue hundred pounds to purchaſe fiue and twentie pounds a yeere for euer,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> To Saint <hi>Botolphs</hi> Biſhopſgate, To Saint <hi>Giles</hi> Cripplegate, To Saint <hi>Leonards</hi> Shoreditch, To Saint <hi>Mary</hi> White-chappell, To Saint <hi>Sepulchres</hi> Pariſh, twentie pounds for ſixtie poore men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> To the <hi>Mercers</hi> a thouſand pounds more, to purchaſe fiftie pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> for thirtie poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or Widdowes of that Company, to be beſtowed in Gownes; Shirts, Hoſe, and Shooes, euery <hi>Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe</hi> for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> He gaue to the poore of <hi>Huntington;</hi> where hee was borne, two thouſand pounds for Almeſ-houſes, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, or Schoole, which they moſt needed, one hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> He gaue to the poore of <hi>Coxall</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> fiftie pounds.</p>
            <p>He gaue to Priſoners, To <hi>Ludgate,</hi> the two <hi>Compters, Bedlam,</hi> and the <hi>Fleet,</hi> a hundred and fiftie pounds, thirtie pounds apiece.</p>
            <p>To the <hi>Kings Bench</hi> and <hi>Marſhallſea,</hi> forty pounds, twenty pounds apiece.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17822:23"/>
            <p>He next turned the right eye of his Charitie vpon the Church and Gods Seruice: As for Sermons at <hi>Mercers</hi> Chappell, from the firſt Sunday in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Tearme, euery Sunday, to the firſt Sunday in <hi>Lent</hi> (except thoſe that fall out in the twelue dayes of <hi>Chriſtmaſſe</hi>) fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds to purchaſe fiue and twenty pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> He hath giuen fiue hundred pounds to purchaſe fiue and twentie pounds a yeere for euer, for a Lecture to be read at Saint <hi>Bartholomewe's</hi> where hee liued, on the Weeke day.</p>
            <p>Hee hath giuen two thouſand eight hundred pounds, to buy in certaine Impropriations, in ſome <hi>Northerne</hi> Counties, where there is leaſt preaching.</p>
            <p>Next his Charitie came vpon the Miniſters, firſt, hee gaue to ſixe by name, the ſumme in all three hundred and thirtie pounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> He gaue twentie Preachers beneficed in <hi>London,</hi> whoſe Liuings were of ſmall value, foure hundred pounds, twentie pounds apiece.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> Hee gaue to twentie vnbeneficed Preachers in <hi>London,</hi> foure hundred pounds, twentie pounds apiece.</p>
            <p>Here is a faire banke of Charitie; In all it amounts to the ſumme of 10726. pounds thirteene ſhillings and foure pence. Beſides that which hee conferred vpon his Company, Kindred, Friends, and Seruants, which runs out to wel-nigh fiue thouſand pounds more. O the large armes of Charitie! And withall, one notable thing which ſtayes my conſideration vpon it. That in all this Magazine of bountie, he hath not made Vſury his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor as ſome doe; Hee would not that his Workes of Charitie ſhould grow out of the blacke roote of Vſury, but that Land ſhould bee purchaſed for the perpetuating of them.</p>
            <p>But to turne in againe one ſhort turne to theſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,<note place="margin">Orator eſt vir bonus dicendi peritus, Iſidor. Etymol. li. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Acts <hi>9.39.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17822:23"/> what coſt of words is able ſufficiently to expreſſe them? I confeſſe, I want one part of an Oratour which is words, yet I want not altogether the other, which is goodneſſe; therefore, I muſt needs with <hi>Dorcas</hi> her Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, at the leaſt ſhew the Coats &amp; Garments of mercy which he gaue. Nay, I will blow this coale a little more, and adde, If God made houſes vpon earth for the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues of <hi>Egypt,</hi> for their mercie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.21.</note> ſurely God hath made him a houſe in Heauen for his mercy; and we haue cauſe to build him ſome Monument of his memory. Bleſſed be that mercy which betakes it ſelfe into the Bowels of the <hi>Poore,</hi> to lodge there! Happy thoſe hands,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.5.</note> which drop ſuch Myrrhe! Let the Poore be your Altars, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Sacrifices are to be offered;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 2.18.</note> And as <hi>Rahabs</hi> houſe was ſaued by the Scarlet Threed, ſo ſhall your workes be the meanes of the ſauing of you, they ſhall bee as the Angels were to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to receiue you into euerlaſting habitations. Let your Charitie ſhine vpon the ſicke; Get you within the ſhadow of this example,<note place="margin">Bibulam ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ſalſugo ambitionis occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pat, Cypr. prolog. in ſermones. Proximorum aperuit ſauces Conſtantinus, ſaginauit Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian. Marcell. lib. <hi>16.</hi> Quid tam po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulare quam li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertas, quam &amp; à beſtijs expeti videmus, Cic. de lege Agraria orat. <hi>2.</hi> Iſidor. Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. lib <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> as ſometimes they did within the ſhadow of <hi>Peter,</hi> and there cure that ouer-ſalt deſire, You haue in getting; that as Fame gaue out of <hi>Constantine,</hi> that he opened mens mouthes, but <hi>Conſtantius</hi> filled them; ſo may this honour euer dwell with you, you worthy Citizens, that your Fathers ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the mouth of the poore, but you filled them.</p>
            <p>Let the Priſoners likewiſe feele the ſoft hands of your mercie. Libertie is a thing which the very beaſts deſire: A Priſoner hath few friends, ſcarce his owne Parents are his friends. Therefore, as curious Grauers looke ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vpon greene Flyes, to recollect their ſcattered ſight againe: So let the ſighes of the poore Priſoners come before you and place your eyes vpon them, that you may worke out that curious worke of your ſaluation with more comfort.</p>
            <p>And let the Miniſters coates haue a little more wooll
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17822:24"/> vpon them; too often bruſhing makes them thred-bare, This deceaſed Gentleman, he giues you ayme; ſcarce any man within the liſt of our memory, who ſhewed more true life of affection to the Miniſters then hee. I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate vnto you the whole Picture of his mercie in this kind by one line.</p>
            <p>A certaine Miniſter in this City, making ſute to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Societie of the <hi>Mercers,</hi> for the renewing of a Leaſe of a houſe, in which the ſaid Miniſter dwelt; The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany allowed him this anſwere, that hee ſhould haue his deſire, with condition of paying fiftie pounds for a fine. The graue Miniſter profeſſing his inabilitie to this ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, the heart of this deceaſed Gentleman did ſo runne ouer with compaſſion that preſently hee ſuggeſted into the eare of a faithfull friend of that Miniſters, that he out of his owne purſe would pay that fine for him: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſuddenly accompliſht, through ſome other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions interleaping, at his death he firmed it, and gaue him fiftie pounds for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But I haſte to that Princely worke of his Charitie, in recalling Impropriations to the Church, where becauſe words are many times like ſmels, which doe not nouriſh, but onely refreſh; and that we ſpeake often to the winde, not to the hearts of men. I deſire you in our Sauiours owne accent, <hi>Who hath eares to heare let him heare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.9.</note>Shall we prouide for mens bodies and not for their ſoules? Shall wee looke to the roofe and not to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall? Will we not commit the cure of a finger to an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull Surgeon, and ſhal we commit mens ſoules to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Miniſters? hath Chriſt redeemed the ſoules of men with his heart bloud (one drop of which carries more worth then a thouſand worlds) and haue wee ſuch broad and wide conſciences as to ſuffer a man that hath but foure pounds a yeere, to ſell a thouſand ſoules to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, for ſcarce ſo many pence? I will not open the wrong
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17822:24"/> veine,<note place="margin">Potiùs ne non ſcriberent, quam vt vera ſcribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</note> to diſpute now the ciuill right that Laymen haue to Tithes; Neither can I now diſpute the diuine right of Tithes, againſt which ſome haue written rather, leaſt they might not write at all, then write the truth and haue thruſt their fleſh-hookes into other mens pots. I dare truſt the records of mine owne reading in one thing there is no diuine right to put holy fleſh into euery gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor to giue Tithes to Lay men; Therefore I could wiſh to lay this burden vpon my friends, nay my enemies not to ſnatch theſe coales from off Gods altar, but to let the <hi>Seraphims</hi> only doe this.</p>
            <p>And if ſuch a man haue this conſecrated gold in his tent that hee cannot, being ouer-maſtred by Neceſſitie well leaue it; I would bee his Authour to perſwade him to waue the tenth ſheaue of his tenth, and to pinch himſelfe rather then God, in prouiding a ſufficient Miniſter; yea I would to God I could perſwade ſome rich men, though they haue not wet their feet in this ſacred oyle, yet not to take vp their ſtanding there onely, to doe no harme but to helpe by their mercie, that the Church may run vpon her owne wheeles againe. As God breathed coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell on <hi>Dauid</hi> when he ſhould heare the ſound of a going in the tops of the Mulberrie trees,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.24.</note> then to beſtir him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> ſo I vpon you, that you by the ſound of the feet of this Gentleman and others (the remembrance of their charitie in this kind) would rank your thoughts in that file, to root out this Ark-robbing <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> Sacriledge. If robbery of a common houſe, and piracie of a ſhip of ordinary fraught, make our blood boile within vs; what may the robberie of Gods houſe, and the piracie of the Ship, where Chriſt is, doe? But now to ſteere my diſcourſe to you of this worthy and famous Companie of the Mercers, whoſe care this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman hath borrowed, as the Prophets widdow did her veſſels to receiue this oyle for others; let me returne you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17822:25"/> his owne words in his owne will, which hee bequeathed you, together with his Charitie. <hi>And I heartily entreat the ſaid Wardens, and Commonaltie for Gods ſake that they will be carefull from time to time, to make choice of ſuch as be well knowne to be honeſt, diſcreet, and learned men, fearing God, and painfull in their Miniſterie, that by their life and doctrine they may winne many ſoules to Christ Ieſus.</hi> Oh what words are here? not words but goads. What heart ſo hard-skind where theſe words cannot enter? I am alreadie ſeaſon'd with an opinion of this Societie, that you will doe all this. If hee had onely ſaid, for his owne ſake and not for Gods ſake, yet you would neuer haue wounded your reputations to haue neglected his deſire. As there was a double mercie reigned in him, not onely to giue, but to be carefull that that which hee had giuen, might runne in the right Channell, ſo let a double care euer accompanie you in your meeting about this occaſion,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.9.</note> that <hi>the Arke may goe by the way of his owne coast to Bethſhemeſh;</hi> Mine owne experience chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thus much to mee, that when the preſentations of theſe new-borne Benefices ſhall bee deuolued vpon you, that many wandring Doues will flie to your Arke; and that the Fountaines aboue and below will bee moued, Power from great ones, and friends among your ſelues, moulded on purpoſe, for ſome priuate ends. Therefore then looke vpon the Picture of this Gentleman, I meane his Will, Let neither Might nor Partialitie blow away that care he entruſted you withall. And though many lines be requiſite to make a faire Image, and many gifts to make a Preacher; yet principally I would ſet forward one requeſt vnto you, that you would adorne your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, not with men too young, and of the firſt head, but with men of temper, whoſe braines were ſetled long ſince; For a Miniſter without diſcretion is like <hi>Sampſon</hi> without his eyes, fitter for a Mill, then a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17822:25"/> Church, and ſo I reſigne the reſt to your wiſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ioyne my ſelfe againe to my former argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall turne the point of this Obiection againſt this Mercy, and ſay that this Gentleman was a ſingle man, and had no children; therefore his Charitie bore the leſſe price (hauing no wayes elſe ſo faire a way to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect it) I now anſwere for his aſhes: Firſt, Many a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle man leaues the World as the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> left their Campe with a noyſe and a tumult, and out of confuſion diſpoſe iuſt nothing. Secondly, Though he had no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yet he wanted not theſe of his name, and kindred, one of which he might haue adopted, and haue powred all this Oyle into one Veſſell; if he would haue hunted as many doe, after a worldly continuance of his name; Whatſoeuer men blatter to the contrary; I ſhall ſtill ſend out my Prayers vnto Heauen, that this Mother of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> this Honourable Citie may bring forth many ſuch Children.</p>
            <p>But enough for his life. If I haue broken my limits and bankes with too long a diſcourſe, I craue pardon, becauſe, though I may haue ouer-runne my ſelfe in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to his perſon, yet I haue not ouer-reacht in the truth of the cauſe.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to his death, which was like <hi>Sampſons</hi> death, no leſſe famous if not more famous then his life: for euer as the premiſes are, ſo is the concluſion; and a good life drawes after it a good death.</p>
            <p>Shall I colour out vnto you his deuout and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble receiuing of the Sacrament in his ſickneſſe? the vſe of which howſoeuer now ſome Opiniaſters after ſo long a diſſent of practice, arraigne at their owne barres,<note place="margin">An iuſtitia &amp; fortitudo fuerint anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia. Sen. ep. <hi>113.</hi>
               </note> (for this is an age to queſtion any thing, euen whether ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues be Creatures) yet lyes it ſo faire to the eye; if wee will not ride all Antiquitie and Reaſon, that they that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17822:26"/> will kick at this,<note place="margin">Nec fi ſolem ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum manibus geſtemus, fidem commodabunt. Lactant. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> will not lend vs their faith, though wee ſhould carrie the Sunne in our hands.</p>
            <p>Shall I ſet before you that iudicious confeſſion of his Faith, which hee made at that time? I cannot vnrip euery peece, thred by thred, the time forbids me.</p>
            <p>Shall I conduct you to the deſire hee had to the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the Church, which was accordingly performed I know there are ſome, who would haue Religion to bee like a coate without ſhape or decencie; who thinke it fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to breake ope heauen gates with an vntempered vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,<note place="margin">Non claue, ſed clauo.</note> then to open them with a key, and theſe with their Iron hornes puſh at this practiſe of the Church, as if it were ſome Syrian, ſome Popiſh rag. But I craue paſſage for a word or two. Firſt, I doe not beleeue that there is the ſame power in the Miniſter, as in God, <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatiuè</hi> by originall and prime power to expiate and purge ſinne,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erè tanquam dei miniſtriab ſolvunt id quod deus ipſe efficit Catechiſ. Rom. pa. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> uum. <hi>15</hi> Haec ſoluendi &amp; ligandi poteſtas non minor eſt in Eccleſia, quam in Chriſto Cuſan. epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> ad Bohemos.</note> nor yet the ſame in ſubſtance, and differing only in degree of eminencie in God, and miniſterie in man; as our aduerſaries auerre; for if it were the ſame in kind with Gods power, whether originally or by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuation to forgiue ſinne, it muſt needes be alwaies effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, as it is in God, and the keyes ſhould neuer erre, which the Papiſts themſelues will not defend, for the key of our abſolution may ſometimes bend or turne round, and not open the gate of heauen, Secondly, if that proper and neuer-erring power of forgiuing ſinnes bee not in the Miniſter, then reaſon binds vs to beleeue that it is ſome other act, improper, and indirect, which is onely attributed to man, in forgiuing ſinnes, as, firſt by diſpoſing a man in the vſe of the word, publicke or priuate, to repentance, and ſo to make him capable of remiſſion of ſinnes. Secondly, vpon probable ſignes of repentance, to pronounce ſuch a man penitent, abſolued. Thirdly, by actuall abſolution of him; as in a Patent the Conditions are firſt drawne. Secondly the Patent
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17822:26"/> is ſealed. Thirdly, it is deliuered and applied: ſo doth Chriſt attribute to the Miniſters for the honour of their Miniſtrie, a neerer act of remiſſion of ſinnes; and ſaith, <hi>Whoſeſoeuer ſinnes yee remit, they are remitted vnto them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23.</note> for hee that onely diſpoſeth a man to forgiueneſſe, or pronounceth him forgiuen, is remotely ſaid to forgiue. Yet this actuall abſolution is not a proper act of forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing neither, namely ſuch a one as hath a direct neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie and phyſicall influence into the effect of abſolution; but onely it is <hi>cauſa moralis</hi> or <hi>concilians,</hi> a cauſe morall, whereupon God is ſtirred vp, ſeeing the preparation of the Penitent, and the abſolution of the Miniſter, that is his owne ordinance, to concurre with that act of the Miniſter and to forgiue ſinnes. And this doth neither too much Idolize this power of forgiuing ſinnes with the Papiſts, nor yet too much tread it vnderfoot with others, whom the falſe fire of their owne Imagination leades to thinke, that the Abſolution appointed by the Church and confirmed with other things by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, is a ſuperfluous and Popiſh obſeruation;<note place="margin">Statut. Eliz. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and that God hath lent no power at all to it. But I will draw in my breath. One thing I am ſure of, that after the receipt of this Sacrament, and the forme of abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, God blew vpon that Garden of Spices, his heart, and raiſed him a great deale of comfort; as others can beare a part with mee in this teſtimonie. Shall I bring forth all his religious ſayings which paſſed from him, during all the time of his ſickneſſe? Amongſt many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Hee did bleſſe God, that hee was to die in ſuch a Religion, where the Miniſters gaped not after dying mens goods, as the Popiſh Prieſts doe, but after their ſoules. For indeed they doe not ſo much giue the ſicke oyle, as take from them; and <hi>vngendo emungunt,</hi> by annointing them they vnskrew the more eaſily their charitie. There were foure Miniſters of vs with him in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17822:27"/> his ſickneſſe, and I dare ſay with a cleare forehead, though wee had a yeelding ſubiect to worke vpon; yet not one of vs parted our lips, to exhale the leaſt gift from him for our owne particulars. As his ſtomacke euer kicked againſt Poperie, ſo was hee a true wouen Proteſtant, and a naturall ſonne of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> inſomuch that though he wanted not the Chariots of Iſrael, (the prayers zealous, and frequent of many for him) yet hee deſired the bleſſing of the Church; I meane the common prayers to be read to him before he ſhould <hi>tradere lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pada,</hi> reſigne his laſt breath: to teſtifie the ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light hee ſuckt from them in his life; and that comfort which he aſſuredly hoped to borrow from them at his death. Shall I lay out his comfortable ſpeeches to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when he ſaw their eyes runne ouer with teares for him, hee would often ſay: <hi>Truſt in God;</hi> for his owne heart taught him, that ſeeing all the pleaſures of this life muſt be rowled together, and all ſhould be filed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that file of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Vanitie of Vanities, all is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anitie,</hi> it was the trueſt wiſedome to hang vpon God.</p>
            <p>Shall I encroach ſo farre vpon your patience as to ſhew you his Patience towards God? All the time that fatall ſickneſſe fed vpon him, euen till death, He lowed not vnder the hand of God, as the Kine did vnder the Arke,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.12.</note> as if he were vnwilling to leaue this world, as they were to leaue their Calfes, but was willing to beare that hand in aduerſitie, that had borne him in proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;<note place="margin">Quadratus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis Chriſtianus, quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris, ſtat. Aug. in Pſ. <hi>86.</hi> homil. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> like a foure ſquared ſtone, which way ſoeuer you throw it, it reſts; ſo did he <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> caſts his paſſions aſleepe, as Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith, and was content what way ſoeuer God came vpon him, whether from the North or the South, in Iudgement or in Mercie.</p>
            <p>Shall I bedew you with his teares? Neuer any man, at whoſe death I haue beene, drew more teares from his eyes then he. Thoſe Limbecks of his neuer ceaſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17822:27"/> Theſe Fountaines aboue were almoſt alwayes open; Surely as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Procella ingens magnam vim ferebat lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum, Aug. Confeſſ. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>12</hi>
               </note> There was ſome great ſtorme within him, againſt ſinne, that brought downe ſuch a floud of teares, yet not without ſome beames of ioy, for he would ſay himſelfe, See you theſe teares? Theſe ſhall be all botled: And certainly we ſaw that vpon his weeping a wonderfull aſſurance of comfort came vpon him: euen as the fire from Heauen followed the water powred vpon <hi>Elias</hi> his Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for his faith and hope, which did aſſiſt him, till his laſt houre; mine eyes were neuer witneſſes of a greater confidence in any dying man, his comfort neuer ſo much as once ſhaken. If hee had had any broken fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in his ſleepe, that might ſeeme to haue ouer-ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed his hope; hee would chaſe them away ſtill, as hee waked. Indeed his confidence was ſo high-built that I began to looke at the foundation; fearing that there might bee ſome bogge of preſumption; and that all was not built vpon the firme Rocke. To that purpoſe, doubting he might be too forward, I ſet him backward to conſider the many ſnares and temptations of this life, which lie as thicke as the rine in Autumne before our feet; and the many ſinnes which oftentimes men of the beſt fame are gored with. He anſwered me, <hi>I confeſſe I haue beene a great and grieuous ſinner; but yet I thanke God; I did euer labour priuatly to make my peace with God againe.</hi> Nay, this he ſealed againe, with a fairer ſtampe, for being askt by me often, why, finding ſuch comfort, he wept ſo much; He regeſted this anſwer,<note place="margin">Ipſa obmuteſcit facundia, ſi ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra ſit conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Ambroſ. in Pſal. <hi>118.</hi> Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> many times together, <hi>Poore Fiſborne ſhall be a Saint.</hi> Thus as the Sun cannot bee without light, no more can goodneſſe bee without hope; And as after ſhowres of Aprill raine, the aire is the ſweeter: ſo after theſe teares of his, was his ioy the more ſenſible, as on the contrary, If the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bee ſicke, the tongue is dumbe; as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:17822:28"/> ſaith; Nay, that it may appeare, that with this very hope hee tooke Heauen, the very laſt word that hee ſpake in this World teſtifie aloud; when, it ſhould ſeeme, reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing with himſelfe, the Paſſion of Chriſt (a cordiall meditation for all dying men) hee crowned his death with theſe Golden words, <hi>I am now hasting to Mount Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uary to my Sauiour:</hi> and ſo after a little more ſand runne out (his glaſſe neuer to be turned againe) in peace and in a good old age, rendred himſelfe into his hands, with whom hee now reſts in that boſome of glory, and ſhall ſo reſt for euer and euer. Onely he hath left the World, as <hi>Lot</hi> left <hi>Sodome,</hi> in ſmoake and combuſtion. Hee that made God heire of his goods; himſelfe the heire of God, and the earth the heire of his bodie; he hath made many friends, the ſorrowfull heires of his memory. As the long looking vpon the Sunne, makes our eyes water: ſo the ſerious remembrance of his Goodneſſe muſt needes fetch out teares; If ſome mens eyes bee dry for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (for many times the deepeſt wounds bleed not ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, nor the greateſt ſorrows weepe ſooneſt) yet my heart whiſpers to me, their hearts are not dry. Nay, our ſorrows for him will yet riſe to a higher tide, when we come here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after more to want him; wee now bury him in the earth; we ſhall then bury him in our hearts. Time will tell them that loued him without a falſe bottome, that in this I haue now ſaid, my tongue ſtrooke not on both ſides, I confeſſe, I diſtruſt not Gods power, nor hath my hope forſaken me, of any mans goodneſſe, but yet mine eyes deſpaire, almoſt euer to ſee a man, with ſuch a retinue of graces: ſo wiſe, ſo louing, ſo iuſt, ſo religious, ſo chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, ſo hopefull in his death; euen all theſe beames con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into one Glaſſe.<note place="margin">Per eandem li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neam ſerram re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocare. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull. de Corona militia, cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> But I muſt not draw my Saw the ſame way againe, as <hi>Tertullian's</hi> phraſe is. I will only ſound myne hoarſe Trumpet once againe, and ſo end.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17822:28"/>
            <p>Farewell, a <hi>Luſtre</hi> to this Citie; Farewell, a glory to his Company; Farewell, a beautie to the Merchants; Farewell, a credit to the place where he liued; Farewell, an honourer of the Church; Farewell, a Patrone of the Poore; Farewell, the ioy of all his Acquaintance; And if any man haue a part in this ſorrow, I haue not the ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt; Farewell, the nobleſt, louingeſt, and faithfulleſt friend that euer poore man had; Farewell, once againe thou ſecond <hi>Nehemiah;</hi> Farewell Text; Farewell Time. Finally, brethren fare you well. Bee yee good <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah's,</hi> like him; vnderprop Gods ſeruice. And God Almightie <hi>remember you;</hi> and neuer <hi>wipe out the good deeds which yee ſhall doe to the houſe of God, and the offices thereof;</hi> From this time forth and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
